A Guide to the Pioneer America Society Photograph Collection, 1968-1994
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Pioneer America Society Photograph Collection 1968-1994
Thomas Balch Library
VC 0025
This collection consists of 36 photographs taken by Henry H. Douglas and William Edmund Barrett. It is divided into two series by photographer, after which it is arranged chronologically. The photographs were taken for "Echoes of Time," the newsletter of the Northern Virginia Chapter of the Pioneer America Society. Most, but not all, were eventually published in the newsletter.
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
Alternative Form Available
Digital surrogates
Accruals
1989.0006
Historical Information
Founded in July 1967 by community activist, historian, and photographer Henry H. Douglas (27 February 1906 - 15 January 1989), the Pioneer America Society (PAS) is committed to documenting, studying, identifying, and preserving architecture and historic artifacts. The organization advocates a balanced approach of blending the old with the new while working to raise awareness about the damage of a "bulldozer mentality" that threatens to sweep away all evidence of our unique cultural heritage. Douglas contributed his work to the PAS newsletter, "Echoes of Time," along with other local photographers, including William Edmund Barrett (20 March 1927 - 12 October 1997).
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 36 photographs taken by Henry H. Douglas and William Edmund Barrett. It is divided into two series by photographer, after which it is arranged chronologically. The first series consist of 26 3.5 x 5 inch black and white photographs; the second series contains 10 8 x 10 inch black and white photographs. Negatives of three photographs from the first series are also included. Photograph titles are taken from the verso of the images, where supplied by the photographer. The photographs were taken for "Echoes of Time," the newsletter of the Northern Virginia Chapter of the Pioneer America Society. Most, but not all, were eventually published in the newsletter.
Series 1 contains 26 photographs taken by Henry H. Douglas, most dating from 1968 to 1994. The photographs are of individuals, bridges, historic homes and structures, and monuments. Series 2 contains 10 photographs taken by William Edmund Barrett dating from 1968 to 1994. The photographs are of historic homes, bridges, barns, and railroads.
Arrangement
Chronological
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Douglas, H.H. Caves of Virginia: Virginia Region of the National Speleological Society. Falls Church, Virginia: Falls Church Historical Commission, 1981.
Douglas, H.H. Falls Church: Places and People. Falls Church, Virginia: Falls Church Historical Commission, 1981.
"Henry H. Douglas," Northern Virginia Sun, January 18 1989, Obituaries.
"Pioneer America Society," About Us. http://www.pioneeramerica.org/about.html (accessed 26 August 2013).
Pioneer America Society Records, Collection #C0011, Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University. http://sca.gmu.edu/finding_aids/pioneer.html (accessed 10 August 2013)
Pioneer America Society. Records, 1929-1984 (bulk 1968-1976). Accession 40235. Organization Records Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219 http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi01266.xml(accessed 26 August 2013
Raitz, Karl B. and Thompson, George F. The National Road. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1996.
William E. Barrett Jr.," The Herald-Mail, October 15, 1997, Obituaries.
Other Finding Aid
Past Perfect Catalog Records
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Henry H. Douglas
    - Va - Loudoun - Stores - Kashway Gen Store, Rt 7, n.d.
    - Va - Loudoun - Stores - Kashway Gen Store, Rt 7, n.d
    - [unidentified house], 14 July 1968
    - Va - Loudoun - Tap Rock Quarry, W&OD roadbed at left. Gondolas were loaded from platform beside roadbed, 28 September 1969
    - Va - Loudoun - Tap Rock Quarry, 28 September 1969
    - Va - Loudoun - Tap Rock Quarry. W&OD roadbed in foreground. Gondolas were loaded from this platform, 28 September 1969
    - Va - Loudoun Co - Grist Mill Ruins - SW of Hillsboro at Jct of 719 & 715, Pots II or Burnt Mill, burned 11/30/1864, 14 June 1970
    - Brade-Roberts Log House, early 19th centruy, see Echoes v. 1 no. 1, p.1 26 July 1970
    - [Broad Run Bridge], 21 April 1973
    - [Broad Run Bridge], 21 April 1973
    - [Broad Run Bridge], 21 April 1973
    - [Broad Run Bridge], 21 April 1973
    - [Broad Run Bridge], 21 April 1973
    - Va - Loudoun -Rds - Rt 50 at Gilberts Corner, January 1975
    - Va-Loudoun-Streams-Crooked Run, near Lincoln, 5 May 1976
    - Va-Loudoun/Lincoln Crooked Run, 5 May 1976
    - Va. Loudoun/Purcellville W&OD Sta [sic, Leesburg stockyard fire], 27 August 1977 ca
    - John Champe marker, 28 October 1978
    - John Champe monument [close up], 28 October 1978
    - John Champe monument, 28 October 1978
    - Va-Loudoun-Bridges (upstream side) [Goose Creek Bridge], 28 October 1978
    - Va-Loudoun-Bridges (upstream side) [Goose Creek Bridge], 28 October 1978
    - Douglas, Henry H. (1906-1989) Va - Loudoun/Hughesville - Geo. I. Crossman, Ann & Ed Becker in Mr. C's flower beds, 24 May 1980
    - Douglas, Henry H. (1906-1989) Va - Loudoun/Hughesville - Geo. I. Crossman, Ann & Ed Becker in Mr. C's flower beds, 24 May 1980
    - Douglas, Henry H. (1906-1989) Va - Loudoun/Lincoln - Ed Becker & Friend, 25 May 1980
    - Douglas, Henry H. (1906-1989) Cummings house, Tom Selby, tenant, My 80, 25 May 1980
  - William Edmund Barrett
    - [house at railroad crossing], n.d.
    - Goose Cr. Bridge, Rt 50. N. Va Calendar, n.d.
    - W & OD Railroad Station, Hamilton looking toward Leesburg, 8 October 1968
    - Evergreen Mills Truss Bridge, 1969
    - Broad Run Bridge & Toll House, April 1973
    - Broad Run Bridge & Toll House, April 1973
    - [Ashburn, unidentified barn], 1975 ca.
    - Va. Loudoun/Arcola - Mill behind Gen. Store, 29 November 1975
    - Va. Loudoun/Arcola - Mill behind Gen. Store, 29 November 1975
    - No. 121 Arriving at Round Hill, Va., 1994